Indiana University Department of Folklore and Ethnomusicology Campus Ghost Walks Records, 1911-2008 C620
Indiana University Archives
Indiana University Department of Folklore and Ethnomusicology Campus Ghost Walks Records
1911-2008
2001-2008
Indiana University Archives
Indiana University, Bloomington. Department of Folklore and Ethnomusicology
C620
1 cubic foot 3 boxes
This collection consists of maps, audio recordings, news reports, advertisements, committee notes, photographs, and story transcripts for the campus ghost walks organized by the Indiana University Department of Folklore and Ethnomusicology. The ghost walks are annual tours that feature ghost legends tied to well-known places on campus and the Bloomington, Indiana, area.
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research. Advance notice required.
Administrative History
The Indiana University Department of Folklore and Ethnomusicology jointly administers the Folklore Institute and Ethnomusicology Institute and offers undergraduate and graduate degrees in both fields. The Folklore Institute at Indiana University began as an eight-week program in the summer of 1942 under the directorship of Professor Stith Thompson. During the program, residential and visiting faculty taught courses on a number of topics, including field collecting and recording, the folk tale and similar forms, folk music and songs, and Native American folklore.
The Folklore Institute grew into a stable research branch of Indiana University's College of Arts and Sciences in 1949 and received departmental status with an independent faculty in 1963. In 1977, the Folklore Institute was named an affiliated institute of the newly designated Department of Folklore.
While ethnomusicology programming began at Indiana University as early as 1948, the field first gained official status at the university through the introduction of the Ethnomusicology Program under the Department of Folklore in 1982. In 2000, the Ethnomusicology Institute was established. That same year, the administrative structure governing folklore and ethnomusicology was reorganized, and the Department of Folklore officially became the Department of Folklore and Ethnomusicology, with the Folklore Institute and Ethnomusicology institute as units within the department.
Since 2001, the Department of Folklore and Ethnomusicology has coordinated annual, ghost-themed campus tours known as "ghost walks." These tours take place during the Halloween season and feature legends tied to well-known campus and Bloomington spaces. Students, staff, and faculty from the department act as organizers, storytellers, and performers for the walks. Past faculty and staff participants include Ruth Aten, Linda Degh, and John Johnson.
Arrangement
The collection is organized into two series: Administrative files and Ghost legends.
Scope and Content Note
This collection consists of maps, audio recordings, news reports, advertisements, committee notes, photographs, and story transcripts for the campus ghost walks hosted by the Indiana University Department of Folklore and Ethnomusicology.
The Administrative Files series (1951-2008) includes materials relating to the coordination of the annual event such as committee notes, correspondence, walking guides, and publicity material, and event photographs. This series also includes a scrapbook documenting the walks from 2002-2005.
The Ghost legends series (1911-2004) contains the collected legends drawn from the Folklore Institute archives that were used to create the content of the walks. Local ghost legends center on campus spaces as well as local Bloomington establishments such as the Porticos Restaurant. Examples of campus ghost legends include those of the Health Center, Well House, the sorority Zeta Beta Tau, and Eigenmann Hall.
Related Material
Additional records such as newsletters, annual reports, bulletins, and publications may be accessed in the Archives of Institutional Memory.
Archived web sites for this Department may be included in Archive-It.
Related photographs may be available in the University Archives Photographs Database.
Acquisition Information
2011/002
Provenance
Records were transferred to the IU Archives in 2011 by John McDowell, Chair of the Folklore department.
Ghosts--Indiana--Bloomington.; Haunted places--Indiana--Bloomington.; Haunted universities and colleges--Indiana--Bloomington.; Indiana University, Bloomington. Department of Folklore and Ethnomusicology -- Archives; Indiana University, Bloomington. Department of Folklore and Ethnomusicology -- Records and correspondence; Indiana University, Bloomington. Department of Folklore and Ethnomusicology -- Faculty -- Archives; Indiana University, Bloomington. Folklore Institute -- Archives
- Administrative files, 1951-2008 (Box 1)
  - Campus Ghost Walk – general files, 2001-2002; (2 folders) (Box 1)
  - Music for ghost walks, undated; (6 CDs and 1 floppy disc) (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, e-mails, 2001-2004 (Box 1)
  - Flyers and posters, 2002-2008 (Box 1)
  - How to Haunt a House, Dan Witkowski, 1995 (Box 1)
  - Indiana Daily Student – collected material (Box 1)
    - General, 1984-2005 (Box 1)
    - Bronze markers, 1951 (Box 1)
    - Baby elephant, 1951 (Box 1)
  - List of stories/participants, 2001-2004 (Box 1)
  - Non-IU ghost stories by students in folk courses, 2001 (Box 1)
  - Organization Committee, undated (Box 1)
  - Photos, 2002-2005 (Box 2)
  - Publicity, 2001-2006 (Box 2)
  - Scrapbook, 2002-2005 (Box 3)
  - Walking guides, undated (Box 2)
- Ghost legends, 1911-2004 (Box 2)
  - Arboretum, 2003 (Box 2)
  - Auditorium, Theatre and Drama, 2004 (Box 2)
  - Ballantine Hall, 2003 (Box 2)
  - Briscoe, 2001-2004 (Box 2)
  - Career Center, 2003 (Box 2)
  - Cemeteries, 1951, 1990, 1996 (Box 2)
  - Delta Tau Delta, 1976 (Box 2)
  - Doctor/Frat House, 1984, 1990 (Box 2)
  - Eigenmann Hall, 1976-2004 (Box 2)
  - Folk/Ethno 504 N. Fess, 1984-2001 (Box 2)
  - Goodbody, 1990 (Box 2)
  - Health Center, 1989 (Box 2)
  - IM Union, 2001-2004 (Box 2)
  - Kappa Delta Rho, 1990-2004 (Box 2)
  - Maxwell House, 2001 (Box 2)
  - McNutt/ Hatchet Man, 2001 (Box 2)
  - Miscellaneous Stories, 1984-2004 (Box 2)
  - Owen Hall, 2001 (Box 2)
  - Pi Beta Phi, 2003 (Box 2)
  - The Pond, 2003 (Box 2)
  - Poplars Ghosts, 2001 (Box 2)
  - Porticos, 1990, undated (Box 2)
  - Read Hall, 1976-2003 (Box 2)
  - Sigma Phi Epsilon, 2002 (Box 2)
  - Teter, 1989-2004 (Box 2)
  - Well House, 1995 (Box 2)
  - Women in Black, 1911 (Box 2)
  - Zeta Beta Tau, 2004 (Box 2)